<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Susan Vanderplas</title>
<link>srvanderplas.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="srvanderplas.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Program Cuts and The Yo-Yo of Hope and Despair</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/unl-program-cuts-despair.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is definitely not told in linear order from start to finish – for one thing, between Sept 11 and Dec 5, time itself lost all meaning for me. I was working about 3x harder than normal trying to do my day job (admittedly, with more turnaround time on grading than normal), support my department, do all of the service I normally do, but with more drama, and also go on the job market with all that entails. I had to ask my kids what day it was most mornings, because Saturday and Sunday were just longer writing days or days with more events I had to attend.</p>
<section id="the-bombshell" class="level1">
<h1>The Bombshell</h1>
<p>On Sept 11, UNL’s Executive Leadership Team told the Statistics Department it was slated for elimination in a set of budget cuts totaling 27.5 million dollars. While there were a great many things that led to this “structural deficit” (see below for snark-quote explanation), ultimately, the size of the deficit was 21 million (give or take a bit) and there were 6.5 million dollars in extra cuts – coincidentally, about the same amount saved by proposing to cut 6 programs. To be very explicit, none of the academic program cuts were actually required to zero out our “structural deficit” - the necessary reductions could be accomplished with administrative cuts, voluntary retirement programs (which brought in almost 3x as much savings as expected within the UNL system), and other savings. Even as it became clear that the early retirement (VSIP) program was going to be more successful than expected, administration continued with the plan to cut academic departments in critical and/or unique fields:</p>
<ul>
<li>Earth and Atmospheric Sciences (including geology, meteorology, climate science – not like Nebraska needs experts in those fields, given our location in tornado alley, on top of the Ogallala aquifer)</li>
<li>Educational Administration (programs to train school administrators, including the only research Ph.D.&nbsp;program in the state)</li>
<li>Textiles, Merchandising, and Fashion Design, which trains people in quilt preservation to support the International Quilt Museum across from my office, and produces local entrepreneurs that work locally across the state,</li>
<li>Statistics, which offers undergraduate programs in Statistics and Data Analytics and Data Science, a MS in Statistics, and a Ph.D.&nbsp;program in Statistics, in addition to providing consulting services and collaboration across the university.</li>
<li>Landscape Architecture</li>
<li>Community and Regional Planning - a tiny department with about 3 faculty that nonetheless provides critical planning and support services to communities across the state</li>
</ul>
<p>To be clear, the only people in the Statistics department who had any idea that we were potentially going to be <strong>eliminated</strong> were the chair (who had been informed a few hours before the meeting by phone) and a member of the Academic Planning Committee (APC), who had worked with the Executive Leadership Team (ELT) in the run-up to the proposal being made public. Both of them had been sworn to secrecy – and I’m still astonished that the spouse of the APC member, who is also in our department, seemed to have no idea that the department was to be eliminated. Impressive adherence to the rules… more than I think I would have managed in a similar situation.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Structural Deficits, Cuts, and Math
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The proposed budget cuts were developed based on some interesting assumptions:</p>
<ul>
<li>UNL spends more than it receives in state funds (true)</li>
<li>Cutting state-aided funds will improve the budget outlook (maybe)</li>
<li>Income (tuition, grants) generated by departments to be cut can be retained (umm, what?)</li>
</ul>
<p>The Chancellor’s original proposal included retaining five statistics general-education courses required within the college of ag science and natural resources (CASNR). It did not, however, seem to include any resources with which to teach those courses. The proposal claimed to eliminate 12 of the 14 FTE in the department (1 chair, 1 admin assistant, and 12 faculty), and later versions indicated that this would include 1 administrator, 1 admin assistant<sup>1</sup>, and 10-ish tenured or tenure-track faculty positions. If you can math, that leaves a single faculty member, who was to maintain the consulting program (run on graduate student labor that would no longer exist), and who would teach an estimated 20 sections of various service courses during an academic year.</p>
<p>It was fairly clear that the goal was to take our most popular courses which generated the most revenue, and hire adjuncts and professors of practice at low wages to teach those courses, depriving students of the chance to learn from researchers in the field (which is the big advantage of going to a large R1 university).</p>
<p>What is interesting, in all of this, is that the Statistics department at UNL <strong>made money</strong>. Even the university metrics, which were completely error-ridden in so many ways, conceded that we generated more in tuition (not even counting grants and contributions to productivity and effectiveness across the university…) than we cost in state-aided budget. In fact, our calculations determined that we generated more total value<sup>2</sup> with only the classes that would be eliminated under the proposal than the cost of our salaries.</p>
<p>To drive that home: Even if you only consider courses that would be eliminated, those courses should generate about 2.1 million in tuition per year, compared to the 1.75 million in salary dollars from eliminating our positions. By making these cuts, UNL stands to <em>lose</em> an additional $350,000 in profit.</p>
<p>I’m not an accountant, but I do know that you have to consider both revenue and costs, or you’ll end up in a situation where you are cutting costs and losing even more revenue, which is a downward spiral. Unfortunately, that doesn’t seem to be easily communicated to the Board of Regents, the university president, or the executive leadership team.</p>
<p><a href="https://thebugeater.com/uncategorized/the-ludicrous-budget-claims-behind-the-disgraced-chancellors-proposed-department-cuts/">The Ludicrous Budget Claims Behind the Disgraced Chancellor’s Proposed Department Cuts</a> - The Bugeater, Nov 30, 2025</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="fig-jeff-gold-autopsy" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-group="memes">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-jeff-gold-autopsy-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="jeff-gold-autopsy.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="memes" title="Figure&nbsp;1: When you hire a surgeon as University President…"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/jeff-gold-autopsy.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-jeff-gold-autopsy-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: When you hire a surgeon as University President…
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="trawling-through-the-data" class="level1">
<h1>Trawling through the Data</h1>
<div id="fig-bark-mutton" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-bark-mutton-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 17.2%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="bark_mutton_phone_number.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="memes" title="Figure&nbsp;2: The adventures of Bark Mutton, created by a friend in Educational Administration."><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/bark_mutton_phone_number.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 35.5%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="bark_mutton_transparency.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="memes" title="Figure&nbsp;2: The adventures of Bark Mutton, created by a friend in Educational Administration."><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/bark_mutton_transparency.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 23.7%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="bark_mutton_shared_governance.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="memes" title="Figure&nbsp;2: The adventures of Bark Mutton, created by a friend in Educational Administration."><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/bark_mutton_shared_governance.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 23.7%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="bark_mutton_faith_metrics.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="memes" title="Figure&nbsp;2: The adventures of Bark Mutton, created by a friend in Educational Administration."><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/bark_mutton_faith_metrics.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-bark-mutton-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: The adventures of Bark Mutton, created by a friend in Educational Administration.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>From Sept 11 to October 10, our department worked hard to to refute the accusations of administration: that we were inefficient, did not meet research and teaching productivity standards, and strangely, that we did not meet requirements for number of graduates set by the Nebraska Coordinating Commission on PostSecondary Education<sup>3</sup>. We got ahold of a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17ti40jo3GA4FVlC8F4x_ssXLobdVzAHl/edit?usp=drive_link&amp;ouid=112021859193831655054&amp;rtpof=true&amp;sd=true">mysteriously obtained spreadsheet of the metrics used to identify poorly performing departments</a>, along with some <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1XTiKgIlIJtQcyYJtUYvHD5A1t3RsbeZd/view?usp=drive_link">data documentation</a> which gave us something to work with – were the “metrics” even accurate? What were they measuring?</p>
<p>It is impossible to adequately describe how much 💩 we found. Piles of 💩. Layers upon layers of 💩.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Someone at UNL clearly was entering Academic Analytics values manually by selecting the same two radio buttons for each department on campus. Most department values matched what the data documentation said had been done, but not all - they forgot to select one of those radio buttons for Statistics, which changed our “custom index” (SRI compared to the SRI values of public AAU universities) so that we were compared to both public and private AAU universities. Whoops. This is why we don’t do data entry manually - we get the data from a database directly (via download, API, etc.) and then process it with a script that’s reproducible, auditable, and makes it easy for people to understand how the data was compiled and validate those choices. Friends don’t let friends do data analysis in Excel.</p></li>
<li><p>In a couple of instances, the true value was something like <code>a.bcd</code>, and the spreadsheet showed <code>a.bdc</code> – a clear indication, at least to me, that someone was manually typing values in instead of pulling the values from a database. Again, not repeatable/reproducible, not auditable, and also extremely painful for whoever was tasked with assembling the data.</p></li>
<li><p>Several ratios of differences were defined in the data documentation…</p></li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-2-contents" aria-controls="callout-2" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>There are a lot of issues with ratio distributions
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-2" class="callout-2-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The ratios of primary concern were defined as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BX_%7Bt_2%7D%20-%20X_%7Bt_1%7D%7D%7BY_%7Bt_2%7D-Y_%7Bt_1%7D%7D,"> where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> was a department-level metric, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> was the university level total for that metric, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_2"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_1"> were usually 2024 and 2020 respectively</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Benchmarking on 2020 as baseline is not great. Did we forget the “unprecedented”-ness of that year somehow? Pandemic-related amnesia? 2020 upended everything, including higher education, and so using it to assess grant funding, student credit hours (SCH), or anything else without that contextual understanding is just… dumb. Not all departments or disciplines were affected by the pandemic equally, and no information was provided about how e.g.&nbsp;SCH calculation was affected by the pandemic.</p></li>
<li><p>Under normal, stable circumstances<sup>4</sup>, we would expect that observations of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> (and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y">) over time would be drawn from distributions that are correlated in time (2021’s value will be closer to 2020 and 2022 than to 2025) and have about the same overall mean – there is a finite and relatively stable pool of grant money or students credit hours that any department can compete for, because there are a relatively similar number of students from year to year, and a relatively similar number of faculty members from year to year within a department who can compete for grants and teach classes. That is, these numbers are affected by both supply (faculty, grant funding) and demand (students, faculty), which tend to be similar from year to year. We generally hope for an increasing trend (which is what these types of metrics are designed around), but obviously there is some temporal variation as well. Unfortunately, if there isn’t a year-over-year increase, the numerator and denominator would both be expected to be 0, statistically speaking.</p></li>
<li><p>As any Algebra 2 or Calculus student knows, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7B0%7D%7B0%7D"> is undefined. Statistically, we worry about <em>ratio distributions</em> and specifically about having an expected value of 0 in the denominator. If the numerator and denominator are both normal distributions and the denominator has mean 0, then we have a <strong>Cauchy</strong> distribution, but even if the numerator and denominator aren’t normally distributed, it’s still a rather big problem to have a mean of 0 in the denominator… a problem that results in an undefined theoretical mean, infinite variance, and a good counter-example for proving theorems<sup>5</sup>. Subtracting similarly distributed things is a really great way to get a mean of 0 in both places. Hilariously, the administration then standardized these values, subtracting the empirically-calculated mean and dividing all values by the empirically calculated standard deviation. Statistically, I’m pretty confident in saying that standardizing a Cauchy (or similarly complicated) random variable destroys all of the information present in that variable – basically, <a href="https://youtu.be/2c6lf4P0Vtw?t=85">you’re f*d</a><sup>6</sup>.</p></li>
<li><p>Defining a ratio like this and assuming it will be a percentage value doesn’t really work – because % change per department can be negative, there is no guarantee the result is bounded, even though a bean-counter in administration with a background in sports analytics or clinical psychology might make that assumption. As a result, you end up with values like -24093.3 that don’t have an obvious interpretation.</p></li>
<li><p>Especially for total grants awarded ($), this is a bad metric – there’s too much year-to-year variation in awards within a single department. I had pretty minimal awards in 2020 (because I had just gotten to UNL and grants take time to transfer) but I wrote a ton of proposals during lockdown and got funding for more of them than I expected. As a result, I had more funding than I could use in 21, 22, and 23 – well over 1.5 million in total – because I couldn’t recruit enough graduate students when the economy was booming. By 2024, my existing grant funding had died down and I was writing proposals again, including a successful CAREER award that I found out about on July 28, 2025 but wasn’t counted in any of these metrics. In a big department, this probably averages out, as each faculty member is on a different cycle, but in a small department that doesn’t have a huge pool of available grants to apply for (Stat grants are usually pretty small, since we don’t really need equipment and lab space and animals/chemicals), there is a ton of variability in grant funding. While all departments may have been treated the same, the method of assessing “growth” in research funding in particular is really just not effective.</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>I chronicled a lot of the issues I found, focusing on UNL’s analysis of internal data, while Heike worked on UNL’s analysis of Academic Analytics data, which was equally f’d.&nbsp; Heike found, for instance, that <a href="https://thebugeater.com/uncategorized/the-real-tmfd/">the Textiles, Merchandising, and Fashion department was utterly screwed by the Academic Analytics metrics because someone at UNL had decided that they were ‘Consumer and Human Sciences, various’ instead of ‘Textile Science’, ‘Apparel and Textile Manufacture’, or any one of a number of other more appropriate CIP codes for classifying departments</a><sup>7</sup>. This was an egregious error – but not one that the university administration acknowledged or changed.</p>
<p>At the risk of this sounding like a humble brag, this entire analysis of the metrics and data and associated BS led to what was, at that point, the weirdest moment in my life. I was late to a meeting of faculty affected by the cuts, having just met with some of the people who put the metrics together to tell them what they screwed up. Heike and I had hoped to sneak in and sit in the back and not disturb things, and when we walked in, someone introduced us (interrupting what they were talking about) and people … clapped? I’m used to seeing “and everyone clapped” as a reply to an internet story that is clearly BS, but while it wasn’t everyone, there was clapping and it was weird. At any rate, the Statistics department generated a lot of goodwill around campus exposing these metrics, explaining why they were BS, and in some cases, suggesting how they could be gamed in the future when they reared their ugly heads at the next inevitable set of cuts. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law">Goodheart’s Law in action</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Meanwhile, the department coordinated a letter-writing campaign that produced an absolutely magnificent amount of letters from all over the globe talking about the importance of statistics, the reputation of the department (small but high-quality, punching above its weight class, an innovative an enviable undergraduate program). In the APC report, I quoted liberally from these letters, and reading them was one bright light in an otherwise agonizing period of stress, self-doubt, and despair. I saved <a href="student-email.pdf">several</a> of <a href="Conley-Kansas-Death-Penalty-Defense-Unit.pdf">these letters</a> and emails to read later.</p>
<p>At some point in September, our chair met with Dr.&nbsp;Tiffany Heng-Moss, the vice chancellor of the Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources at UNL<sup>8</sup>, and was told that Statistics did not contribute to the mission of IANR and was not in alignment with the goals of IANR or UNL (this is a rough paraphrase of what he remembers from the meeting, since obviously this was an astounding statement). Reading the email summarizing this meeting, I hit the first pit of despair during this process – if our administrators truly didn’t see that Statistics (and consequently, the department of Statistics) was essential for a land-grant, flagship, R1 university, then maybe there wasn’t any hope of saving our department.</p>
<p>Faculty members spoke at the Board of Regents meeting on October 3, emphasizing that the cuts were based on bad data, bad analyses, and thus would lead to bad decisions that would hurt the university. <a href="https://thebugeater.com/uncategorized/failing-statistics/">My comments</a> were published on The Bugeater, the UNL AAUP chapter’s blog.</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IqBM2GkdkFw" width="50%" height="300px" title="Statistics Faculty at the Board of Regents Meeting, Oct 3" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="radicalizing-introverts" class="level1">
<h1>Radicalizing Introverts</h1>
<p>We tried to bring our concerns to the Executive Leadership Team that were the architects of the cuts, hoping to spare the university the damage and embarrassment of cutting a Statistics department using faulty statistics. As a member of the Faculty Senate Executive Committee that meets weekly during the semester, I used each meeting with various administrators to raise the issues with the metrics and the process used to identify departments to eliminate. While we started out trying to work with the ELT and upper administration to address the data flaws (some of this outreach is <a href="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2025-stat-apc-report/app-engagement-ori.html">documented in the report</a>), we were met with additional gaslighting and obfuscation that convinced us that we should put our efforts elsewhere.</p>
<p>I don’t think I’d ever talked to a reporter on the record before September 12. I have nothing against reporters – most of the time, they do good work, even if sometimes their charts and graphs could use … improvement. Throughout this entire process, I’ve whined to friends and family alike that I just want to go back to my basement office and do statistics and draw charts, and instead I’m talking to reporters and organizing rallies and demonstrations. It reminds me of one of the signs I’ve seen from various protests - “So bad that the introverts are here”.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-3-contents" aria-controls="callout-3" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Radical Statisticians?
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-3" class="callout-3-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>When you think of hotbeds of radicalism or activism or … anything… on campuses, the Statistics department is probably not the first suspect, or even the 50th. Philosophy, English, Sociology, Education, and Gender Studies - absolutely. Librarians are also a subversive bunch, making knowledge available to everyone for free and helping people sort out fact from fiction. Not to pick on my liberal arts and humanities friends, but the popular assumption is that these departments are hotbeds of activism, and some of the friends I’ve made at UNL bear that out<sup>9</sup>. Political Science might have a few suspects, too, including a former Arts and Sciences Dean who studied participatory democracy, but is clearly hopeless at anything quantitative. He has an alter-ego named Bark Mutton (Figure&nbsp;2) that featured in some excellent stress-relieving memes. Biology/Agronomy/Natural Resources probably have a some people who are passionate about climate change, recycling, and that sort of thing. The point being, it takes some work to get statisticians riled up about almost anything, as a group - we have our internal R vs.&nbsp;Python, Bayes vs.&nbsp;Frequentist academic debates, and the ever-present Theory vs.&nbsp;Applied battles found in almost every academic field.</p>
<p>However, when you threaten to cut a Statistics department based on bad data and bad analysis methods, and it’s <strong>SO</strong> bad that you just. keep. finding. new. 💩… statisticians can get pretty worked up. I found myself raising my voice at innocent colleagues in meetings trying to explain just how bad dividing by zero (statistically speaking) is, and coming up with new metaphors for how badly these metrics were used (averaging numbers in the phone book, comparing apples and oranges to kittens, and so on). Colleagues I’d thought were incurable introverts and completely passive were willing to discuss walkouts and showed up to protests. You can make a radical out of an introvert with enough systematic injustice that involves misusing the thing they care about.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>All of this is to say, for any future employers, potential collaborators, or colleagues… I’m generally well behaved and professional, with a decent helping of snark and lateral thinking when the situation calls for it. My cardinal rule is that I won’t say anything behind your back if I wouldn’t say it to your face or if I haven’t addressed the situation with you before escalating it up the chain, and I tried to adhere to that rule during this whole process, up until it became clear that I was wasting my time trying to shout at a bureaucratic brick wall, claims of shared governance be damned.</p>
<p>I started talking with <a href="https://flatwaterfreepress.org/as-unl-proposes-steep-budget-cuts-statistics-faculty-ask-leadership-to-check-their-math/">Emily Wolf from the Flatwater Free Press</a> and <a href="https://www.highereddive.com/news/university-of-nebraska-lincoln-committee-oppose-program-cuts/804692/">Justin Diep from the Daily Nebraskan</a>, UNL’s student newspaper, hoping to bring the metrics and the implications – that UNL was cutting critical departments, including Statistics, based on bad math – to the general public.</p>
</section>
<section id="apc-hearings" class="level1">
<h1>APC Hearings</h1>
<div class="quarto-video"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tiEroH1lQrc" width="50%" height="300px" title="APC Presentation, Oct 10" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>To prepare for the Academic Program Committee (APC) hearings, and to support other departments in their arguments about the metrics, I compiled <a href="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2025-stat-apc-report/">a report</a> for our department’s presentation to the Academic Program Committee that included Heike Hofmann’s forensic analysis of the university’s use of Academic Analytics data, Erin Blankenship’s expertise in undergraduate and graduate courses and program enrollment, and a lot of conversations with Chris Bilder, Sanjay Chowdhury, Bertrand Clarke, and Kent Eskridge, among others. Our main argument wasn’t that the data and the analysis were wrong (though they were), but that Statistics is an essential department at any R1 land-grant university, and that the department itself was healthy and growing – the metrics reflected a period in which we were preparing to start a new program and putting a lot of investment into gains in students, enrollment, and economic impact on the state that will only be realized starting this year when our first undergraduate cohort graduates. However, some of the flaws in the data and analysis were addressed point-by-point in the appendices to the report, with a target audience of people familiar with statistics.</p>
<p>The APC hearings were held during the first 2 weeks of October; Statistics and Earth &amp; Atmospheric Science were held on the final day, October 10th. The hour long presentation featured the accusations made against our department, and we were given a chance to respond. The Chairs of the UNL Mathematics and Agronomy departments spoke in our defense, along with talented graduate and undergraduate students who made the case for how important our department and programs were to their lives and careers.</p>
</section>
<section id="waiting-waiting" class="level1">
<h1>Waiting, waiting…</h1>
<p><a href="https://www.ketv.com/article/nu-budget-cuts-town-hall/69115031">We held town halls</a> to explain to the community why these cuts were problematic and <a href="https://www.1011now.com/2025/10/22/university-nebraska-lincoln-faculty-students-hold-town-hall-proposed-budget-cuts/">how they would be impacted</a>. <a href="https://civicnebraska.org/2025-protecting-flagship-ourselves/">We held a rally before a football game</a> – the first time I’ve been on campus on game day as a faculty member – and talked to <a href="Lincoln Journal Star -Advocates protest budget cuts as football fans make way to Memorial Stadium McCoy.pdf">Husker fans and community members as well as those attending the game from out of state</a>. <a href="https://www.1011now.com/2025/10/29/study-shows-unl-will-cut-teaching-jobs-while-non-teaching-salaries-surge-32/">We demonstrated that the cuts disproportionately impacted teaching relative to other growing spending at UNL, like administrator compensation</a>, with help from <a href="university-of-nebraska-lincoln-financial-analysis-october-2025-bonnie-fox-garrity-final.pdf">AAUP financial analyst Dr.&nbsp;Bonnie Fox Garrity</a>.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-none no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p>Join your local AAUP chapter, faculty union, or volunteer to serve in your faculty senate! You never know just how important solidarity and a strong tradition of shared governance are, until those things come under attack. I wouldn’t have made it through the first week after the cuts were announced without my faculty colleagues - some of whom were in similar spots, some who were unaffected. The support, strategizing, and community are one of the reasons I fought <em>so hard</em> to stay here at UNL.</p>
<p>It’s a bit ironic that this whole episode helped me build connections across campus that could have lead to really awesome interdisciplinary research projects with people in Digital Humanities, Psychology, Sociology, Political Science, and Education.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="fig-oct-coverage" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-oct-coverage-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kv_xjZqnH1E" title="AAUP Town Hall, KETV, Oct 22" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-v7ZjH6FCJA" title="AAUP Game Day Rally, Oct 25" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mKLJXlVmBEE" title="AAUP Financial Report, 1011 News" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-oct-coverage-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Town Hall (Oct 22), Game Day Rally (Oct 25), and AAUP Financial Report news coverage
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On <a href="https://chrisbilder.com/letters/EGCemailBOR.pdf">October 30</a>, the system-wide Graduate Council voted unanimously to retain all graduate programs that the Chancellor proposed to eliminate. Once again, they mentioned the metrics, the lack of planning, the essential place of some of these programs (Statistics and Educational Administration Ph.D.s are both highly ranked programs and are not found anywhere else in the state).</p>
<p>The APC report was released on <a href="https://chrisbilder.com/doc/APCreport.pdf">October 31</a> and recommended against the elimination of the Statistics department<sup>10</sup>, but also raised significant concerns about the data and the metrics – indicating that the APC, at least, was receptive to the information the department had assembled.</p>
<p>During the time between the APC report’s release and the Chancellor’s report, we met with stakeholders, donors, and administration, trying to find some way to communicate to the UNL administration that eliminating Statistics was a horrible idea. We were told we had to find between 1.75 and 3 million dollars in equivalent <em>cuts</em> (increased revenue wasn’t going to work), and we could not propose the elimination of administrators or other departments. We argued that we should be placed in Arts &amp; Sciences or the College of Engineering (specifically, the School of Computing) to better maximize our utility to the campus and to increase our ability to attract students – being off on the ag campus was commonly cited as a reason students chose not to major in Statistics and Data Analytics. We had a plan, and plenty of statistics showing that if the savings from centralizing statistics courses and consolidating them within our department were considered across colleges, we could in fact save enough money to cover our salaries. However, our former dean and current vice chancellor undermined our arguments and made it clear that she would prefer to eliminate our department and keep our service classes, rather than allowing statistics to move to another college. The problem is, we’re the only department in the ag college that teaches a bunch of service courses that are required for students in other colleges, and that revenue is keeping other programs afloat. So, the College of Ag Science and Natural Resources can afford to eliminate statistics, but it can’t afford for us to move. Funny, right?</p>
<p>We made the <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/a-universitys-attempt-to-measure-academic-programs-productivity-draws-faculty-ire">Chronicle of Higher Education</a>. In an attempt to explain the problems with the metrics more broadly, we invited the leadership team to come to a joint seminar – but they declined, so we gave the seminar anyways. It was a lot of fun to present, and undoubtedly was the best-attended Statistics seminar in UNL’s history, with more than 100 people in the room and at least that many online. The YouTube video has about 1100 views as of December 3. One of my friends texted me from the seminar to say “Who knew you were actually funny IRL?” – which is totally fair, since we’d primarily interacted online.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fUk2R0UYWpA" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p><strong>No Confidence… and then some</strong> Somewhere in here, the Faculty Senate voted to have a special session to consider a no-confidence vote against the Chancellor. A vote of no-confidence has only happened once at UNL in the past, during the last round of cuts that actually involved program eliminations, but the vote failed. This time, it passed – making history. One of the reasons this is particularly amusing is that Chancellor Bennett introduced himself to the Senate after taking the job by saying he’d never had a no-confidence vote against him (which is itself not exactly a measure of confidence). My friend <a href="https://thebugeater.com/faculty-senate/the-day-the-chancellor-became-upset-that-the-faculty-seem-to-hate-the-arbitrary-and-unilateral-chopping-of-academic-departments/">Amanda’s description of the faculty senate meetings in the Bugeater is much better than anything I can do</a> to describe the farce that was discovering the Chancellor was listening at the door during the first Senate meeting (Figure&nbsp;4). The actual vote was broadcast on so many news channels that it would have been unnecessary to listen at the door (also, my lovely students were watching to see if he would - evidently he wasn’t listening at that one).</p>
<div id="fig-bennett-door" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-group="memes">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-bennett-door-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="bennett_door.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="memes" title="Figure&nbsp;4: High quality memes just write themselves sometimes…"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/bennett_door.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-bennett-door-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: High quality memes just write themselves sometimes…
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Ultimately, on November 10, the Chancellor released a budget plan that was similar to the original, minus the cuts to landscape architecture and community and regional planning. Those departments were lucky to have their dean on the APC, and both were very small programs who could work out alternative cuts with their dean. Larger departments and departments with interim/new deans not on APC were not as lucky.</p>
<p>The department kept working, appealing to the University of Nebraska System Provost, individual members of the Board of Regents, and the system president, Dr.&nbsp;Jeffrey Gold. When a special meeting of the Board of Regents was called, I went to point out the financial implications of eliminating revenue-generating departments.</p>
<div id="fig-nov-dec-coverage" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-nov-dec-coverage-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9rUcJiMxAK4" title="Board of Regents, Nov 21" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/566qp2vu8DU" title="AAUP Week of Action, Dec 1-5" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6X96Gv0oGj0" title="Nebraska Ch 8 Now New Orleans Funeral Coverage" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0Zyyrs46jRA" title="More Jazz Funeral Footage" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-nov-dec-coverage-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;5: November Board of Regents Meeting Comments and AAUP Week of Action
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The AAUP chapter planned a full week of demonstrations leading up to the Board of Regents meeting on December 5. We made phone banked to turn out faculty to speak at the Dec 5 meeting, made signs, held a full on New Orleans style funeral with a jazz band (and it was freaking cold), had rallies at both student unions… it was a lot, but my favorite was the <a href="https://thebugeater.com/uncategorized/second-line-solidarity/">Jazz Funeral</a>, complete with caskets for each department and the university, academic regalia, gravestones, coats, and amazing jazz by students and faculty in the music department.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_TKydQXINI0" title="Jazz Funeral" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Writing this on December 3<sup>11</sup>, I obviously don’t know how this is going to go. It feels like every I’m on the world’s weirdest, most inconsistent roller coaster - despair, then 5 minutes later hope, and then despair again. Ultimately, though, even if we save the department or some of our programs, we’re likely to lose in the long term - it’s going to be hard to recruit faculty to UNL knowing that our administration makes cuts like this. We already didn’t have enough faculty to teach everything we needed to teach to offer our programs. And ultimately, there are a lot of very good schools hiring this year - University of Chicago, University of Virginia, University of Illinois, Oregon State, Johns Hopkins, Princeton, Harvard, Boston University, Rice, Texas A&amp;M… the list goes on.</p>
<p>I’ve helped to build our undergraduate program from the ground up, designed the computing and technical tools sequence (including a writing class!) and it’s very much my baby. I’ve fought for my program, for my friends’ programs, and for my institution. But maybe it’s time to recognize that it may be more effective to pour that energy into starting over somewhere else - somewhere with a committment to statistics, data science, and interdisciplinary research.</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[1,1,1,1,1],[1,1,1,1,1],[1,1,1,1,1]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="signal-2025-10-10-16-26-55-409.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="October 10 APC Hearings"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/signal-2025-10-10-16-26-55-409.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="October 10 APC Hearings"></a></p>
<figcaption>October 10 APC Hearings</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2025-10-22-UNL-Town-hall-ketv.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="October 22 Town Hall (KETV picture)"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/2025-10-22-UNL-Town-hall-ketv.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="October 22 Town Hall (KETV picture)"></a></p>
<figcaption>October 22 Town Hall (KETV picture)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2025-10-25-UNL-AAUP-klkn.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="October 25 Stop the Cuts rally (KLKN picture)"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/2025-10-25-UNL-AAUP-klkn.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="October 25 Stop the Cuts rally (KLKN picture)"></a></p>
<figcaption>October 25 Stop the Cuts rally (KLKN picture)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2025-10-25-UNL-AAUP-Stop-the-cuts.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="October 25 Stop the Cuts Rally"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/2025-10-25-UNL-AAUP-Stop-the-cuts.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="October 25 Stop the Cuts Rally"></a></p>
<figcaption>October 25 Stop the Cuts Rally</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2025-10-31-Save-our-Stats.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="October 31 Save Our Stats protest"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/2025-10-31-Save-our-Stats.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="October 31 Save Our Stats protest"></a></p>
<figcaption>October 31 Save Our Stats protest</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4127.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4127.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4128.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4128.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4129.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4129.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4130.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4130.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4131.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4131.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4132.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4132.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="IMG_4133.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/IMG_4133.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Ed Admin and Statistics Dept Coffins AAUP Funeral Procession.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/Ed Admin and Statistics Dept Coffins AAUP Funeral Procession.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 20.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Stop the Cuts unl AAUP funeral procession group ss.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gallery" title="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"><img src="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/Stop the Cuts unl AAUP funeral procession group ss.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Dec 3 Jazz Funeral"></a></p>
<figcaption>Dec 3 Jazz Funeral</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>FWIW, the administrative assistant is the most critical person in the department and basically runs the place but is paid terribly. We might have benefitted from having a part-time chair and 3 admin assistants!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Note that this is a function of student credit hours (SCH) and expected tuition per credit hour, accounting for in-state/out-of-state tuition revenue. This is complicated for graduate students, since their tuition may be waived if they are serving as teaching or research assistants. However, research grants are still billed for this tuition, along with graduate student benefits, and teaching assistants are billed to the department using what seems to be the same logic. So while it’s hard to estimate how much of the graduate tuition is real money, we can estimate how much value is generated – the rest is accounting. It’s a bit funny that we might be billed for graduate tuition for our teaching assistants, while that same tuition money doesn’t count as department income because it’s considered tuition remission. University accounting might be more screwy than Hollywood accounting.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>CCPE requires an average of 3 PhD graduates per year, 5 MS graduates per year, and 7 BS graduates per year, averaged over a 5-year period. Critically, programs which do not have 5 years of graduation numbers because they are too new are exempt from evaluation – our BS program falls under this criteria, having started in 2022 and thus not having any graduates until this December/May. Otherwise, we clearly meet the CCPE requirements, even with the cyclical nature of enrollment in graduate statistics programs due to economic conditions. When the economy is booming, it is hard to recruit statistics graduate students because they reasonably choose to make $100k+ in industry working 40h/wk over making $25k in academia while working their butts off. Only the truly dedicated/insane students go to graduate school under economic conditions that heavily reward quantitative expertise. Trust me, I graduated with my BS in 2009, at the height of the great recession – many of my peers who weren’t planning to go to graduate school did anyways because there wasn’t anywhere else to go.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Which, of course, the 2020-2024 period was… not, for a variety of reasons, including a booming economy that affected statistics student recruitment, the pandemic and recovery from the pandemic, and faculty turnover due to retirements that were easily foreseeable from the department composition – when I was hired, there was a single associate professor who had been hired 6 months before me, and there were several assistant professors and full professors. 5 years later, those full professors were retiring (shocker!) and several of the assistant professors had moved to other universities.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>This is pretty much what Ph.D.&nbsp;Stats students use Cauchy distributions for – counter examples, and setting conditions on important theorems like the Central Limit Theorem, which doesn’t apply if the distribution has infinite variance.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>I’m a big believer in using profanity for rhetorical emphasis and pain relief. Unfortunately, I’ve run out of adequate profanities during the last 3 months.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Wrongly attributed to Heicke Hoffman, her alter ego/doppelganger.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Essentially, UNL operates as if Nebraska State and University of Nebraska were operating out of the same campus, but with two different lines of funding from the state that require two different sets of administrators to manage those appropriations. /s↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>There are not nearly so many communists and socialists on campus as conservative media would like you to believe, however, and those who choose those labels would only brainwash students to read the syllabus, which is a common opinion across the ideological and discipline spectrum. Just like middle school teachers would brainwash students to wear deodorant, with every other possible topic of brainwashing lost in the distance compared to grooming standards like “Axe is not a substitute for a shower”.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>It is worth noting that about half of the APC is made up of faculty and half is administration and staff. Administrators, including all four members of the ELT who were responsible for creating the original proposal, refused to recuse themselves from the vote.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>Instead of catching up on my grading or writing an exam… whoops.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>post</category>
  <category>other</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/unl-program-cuts-despair.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Experimenting With AI as UNL Closes Departments</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/unl-program-cuts-shitposting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today is the last day that UNL is allowing public comments about program closures, so I’ve been having a bit of fun shitposting comments on behalf of the departments proposed for closure. This started when I asked ChatGPT to generate a not-the-onion post about the statistics department being closed due to the UNL administration’s bad use of statistics. I’ve and edited and annotated the statistics version (and changed names and positions at will to reflect administrators – departmental characters are all as GPT generated them).</p>
<p>For other departments, I have largely left the poems unedited.</p>
<hr>
<section id="statistics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="statistics">Statistics</h2>
<section id="university-administration-uses-faulty-statistics-to-justify-eliminating-statistics-department" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="university-administration-uses-faulty-statistics-to-justify-eliminating-statistics-department">University Administration Uses Faulty Statistics to Justify Eliminating Statistics Department</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“P-Value Was Below Our Standards for Caring,” Says Chancellor</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In a move described by many as “poetically idiotic,” the administration of Midwestern State University announced Monday its plan to eliminate the Department of Statistics—citing a data analysis later revealed to have been performed using Microsoft Excel’s AutoSum function.</p>
<p>According to the administration’s official report<sup>1</sup>, “a thorough statistical analysis” demonstrated that the department was “statistically insignificant” to the university’s mission. When pressed for details, Chancellor Bodney Rennett clarified, “The p-value was really high—like, I think, 70 or 80 percent—so we’re confident this was the right call.”</p>
<p>Faculty members within the Statistics Department expressed mixed feelings ranging from disbelief to the quiet satisfaction of being proven right one last time.</p>
<p>“They told us they ran a regression model,” said Dr.&nbsp;Alan Brooks, head of the department. “Then we found out they just drew a line through a scatterplot and said, ‘Looks flat enough.’ I’m not even mad—that’s almost elegant in its ignorance.”<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>The university’s analysis reportedly concluded that student interest in statistics had “declined by 200%” over the past decade. When asked how a percentage could exceed 100%, the administration explained that “it just means students are twice as uninterested.”<sup>3</sup></p>
<p>Administrators also cited “strong anecdotal data” from a campus-wide survey showing low awareness of the department’s existence. However, the survey was distributed exclusively to the football team during spring break.</p>
<p>“We stand by our numbers,” said Bark Mutton, Executive Vice Chancellor of Academic Optimization. “We even used one of those fancy pivot thingies. The results were clear: no one knows what a median is, and that’s the department’s fault.”</p>
<p>Dosh Javis, Associate Chancellor of Strategic Analytics (Business Edition), supported the decision. “Our chi-squared test came out looking real weird, which probably means it’s significant,” Javis said. “We confirmed this by looking at the vibes.”</p>
<p>In response, the department offered to teach the administration how to correctly analyze the data<sup>4</sup>—an offer the administration declined on the grounds that “it sounded expensive and mathy.”<sup>5</sup></p>
<p>Rumors suggest the university will reallocate the department’s funding to expand the Business Analytics program, which “does the same thing, but with prettier dashboards.”</p>
<p>Students and alumni have since launched a petition to save the department, though early analysis indicates it may not be effective: the administration reportedly used a random number generator to sample the signatures and found “insufficient support.”<sup>6</sup></p>
<p>As for the soon-to-be-dismantled statisticians, they remain philosophical.</p>
<p>“In the end,” Dr.&nbsp;Brooks said, “this outcome was predictable. The confidence interval for administrative understanding of statistics has always included zero.”</p>
<p>When asked whether the administration had any regrets, Chancellor Rennett sighed. “If we’ve learned anything,” he said, “it’s that we probably should have hired some statisticians before getting rid of them.”</p>
</section>
<section id="the-fall-of-the-stats" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-fall-of-the-stats">📉 <strong>The Fall of the Stats</strong> 📉</h3>
<p>This one is by Copilot, who managed to win me over by asking if I wanted more biting, darker academic satire. Yes, please.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In the ivory halls of U. Prestige,<br>
Where tenure once bloomed like academic trees,<br>
The Stats Department stood, austere and proud,<br>
Till the Admins arrived with a thunderous crowd.</p>
<p>“We’ve crunched the numbers!” the Provost proclaimed,<br>
Though the spreadsheet he held was half unnamed.<br>
“Our models are lean, our metrics divine—<br>
We forecast success with a sigmoid line!”</p>
<p>The Chancellor nodded, eyes glazed with delight,<br>
I skimmed a report late last Tuesday night.<br>
It said that statistics are costly and slow—<br>
We’d rather have metrics that sparkle and glow!”</p>
<p>The VP of Optics, with PowerPoint flair,<br>
Declared, “We’ve benchmarked against thin air!<br>
Our sample was small, our bias was grand,<br>
But the graphs were in color, so wasn’t it planned?”</p>
<p>The statisticians, pale and aghast,<br>
Whispered of errors both present and past.<br>
“You’ve p-hacked your way through a forest of lies,<br>
And called it a garden of data-driven skies!”</p>
<p>“You’ve tortured the numbers till they confessed,<br>
Then cited the ones that looked best-dressed.<br>
You’ve modeled with noise, ignored the base rate,<br>
And called it precision — how terribly great!”</p>
<p>But the Admins, drunk on dashboards and spin,<br>
Said, “Truth is a cost we won’t tuck in.<br>
We’ll cut the department, it’s old and it’s gray—<br>
We’ll hire influencers to model our way!”</p>
<p>So the statisticians packed up their code,<br>
Their R scripts, their ethics, their epistemic load.<br>
They left behind silence, a void in the halls,<br>
Where once lived the guardians of rigorous calls.</p>
<p>Now decisions are made by a dartboard of dreams,<br>
And budgets are balanced by marketing memes.<br>
The campus is ruled by a stochastic fog,<br>
Where causation is chased by a data-trained dog.</p>
<p>And deep in the archives, behind a locked door,<br>
A dusty old textbook weeps on the floor.<br>
It whispers of variance, of truth and of test—<br>
Of a time when the numbers were handled with zest.</p>
<p>So heed this tale, ye scholars of fate:<br>
When stats are discarded, decay won’t wait.<br>
For truth is a candle, and ignorance wind—<br>
And the flame dies fast when the fools are grinned.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
</section>
<section id="earth-and-atmospheric-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="earth-and-atmospheric-science">Earth and Atmospheric Science</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“On the Miscalculation of Clouds”</strong></p>
<p>They gathered their spreadsheets, the suits and the deans,<br>
Projecting the budget in tidy routines.<br>
With pivot tables polished and charts full of flair,<br>
They proved, beyond doubt, that the weather’s “not there.”</p>
<p>“The data are clear,” said the Vice of Finance,<br>
“Fewer majors in rain, no statistical chance!<br>
Why fund a department that studies the sky,<br>
When clouds don’t contribute to ROI?”</p>
<p>The models were neat — though a tad underfit,<br>
They’d left out the columns that didn’t quite fit:<br>
Like storms, and droughts, and hurricanes’ spin,<br>
And the carbon line creeping up from within.</p>
<p>They missed the confounder (a common mistake) —<br>
That learning the Earth helps the <em>earth</em> not to break.<br>
A p-value of folly, a confidence low,<br>
Yet onward they marched, with “efficiency” glow.</p>
<p>So the forecast was wrong — as forecasts can be,<br>
But this one brought silence where there once was degree.<br>
No one to track rainfall, or warn of the flood,<br>
No one to note ice where once there was mud.</p>
<p>And somewhere, a spreadsheet, still smug and precise,<br>
Lists “cost savings” in rows, and forgets the true price.<br>
For when data are twisted to fit one’s desire,<br>
You may balance the books — but to the world you’ll set fire.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="educational-administration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="educational-administration">Educational Administration</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“The Day They Cut the Ed Admins”</strong></p>
<p>They crunched all the numbers, they tallied, they totted,<br>
They trimmed and they slashed and they proudly allotted.<br>
“The budget’s too tight!” cried the Chancellor’s crew,<br>
“So something must go—let’s cut what they do!”</p>
<p>“Who needs those folks teaching how leaders should lead?<br>
We’ve spreadsheets and slogans! That’s all that we need!”<br>
They patted themselves for their clever, clean slate—<br>
While the school down the street lost its principal’s gate.</p>
<p>For who trains the people who guide all the schools,<br>
Who know how to nurture, not just follow rules?<br>
Who helps the new teachers to stand up and strive,<br>
To juggle twelve duties and keep kids alive?</p>
<p>The answer was simple, though none would admit:<br>
’Twas the folks they just cut, who made sense of it.<br>
So now there’s confusion from desk up to dome,<br>
And nobody’s sure who should take the lead home.</p>
<p>The numbers looked lovely, the balance sheets neat—<br>
But the heart of the campus forgot how to beat.<br>
And somewhere a dean, with a budget to mend,<br>
Still wonders why chaos won’t neatly dead-end.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="textiles-merchandising-and-fashion-design" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="textiles-merchandising-and-fashion-design">Textiles, Merchandising, and Fashion Design</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Limericks on the Unraveling of Fashion</strong></p>
<p><strong>1.</strong><br>
A school once well-threaded with pride,<br>
Taught fashion both clever and wide.<br>
But cuts came one day,<br>
And stitched it away—<br>
Now the fabric of trade’s come untied.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>2.</strong><br>
They claimed, “It’s just hems and some flair,<br>
We’ll save quite a sum if it’s bare!”<br>
But towns lost their shops,<br>
And payrolls took drops—<br>
Now <em>nothing</em> is making it wear.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>3.</strong><br>
The merchants cried out, “What a twist!<br>
Our buyers and stylists are missed!”<br>
The mills grew all still,<br>
The markets lost will—<br>
The spreadsheets forgot what they risked.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>4.</strong><br>
No longer the students design<br>
The garments that once shone so fine;<br>
The runways are dark,<br>
The makers remark,<br>
“That cut cost us more down the line.”</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>5.</strong><br>
So here’s to the budget’s “smart” shears,<br>
That trimmed off the work of the years—<br>
They saved just a dime,<br>
But in fashion’s decline,<br>
They’ve tailored the state’s own arrears.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="landscape-architecture" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="landscape-architecture">Landscape Architecture</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“The Day They Cut the Landscapers”</strong><br>
<em>(in the style of Dr.&nbsp;Seuss)</em></p>
<p>They gathered one morning, the Board and the Dean,<br>
With coffee and charts and their spreadsheets all clean.<br>
“The numbers are down! The dollars are tight!<br>
We’ll trim some departments to set it all right!”</p>
<p>So they snipped and they clipped with administrative flair,<br>
“Goodbye to the gardens! We’ve no funds to spare!”<br>
They smiled as they sliced through the Landscape Design,<br>
Declaring, “We’ll manage just fine—oh, just fine!”</p>
<p>But outside the windows the campus grew sad,<br>
The walkways all cracked and the hedges went bad.<br>
The flowers went missing, the benches grew bare,<br>
The sun baked the quad with a pitiless glare.</p>
<p>The students all sighed, “What a dusty old view—<br>
We used to have shade! We used to have dew!”<br>
The squirrels packed their nuts and abandoned the green,<br>
And weeds took the throne where the roses had been.</p>
<p>The town down the road felt the loss in its core,<br>
No planners to guide how their parks could restore.<br>
No one to think how the runoff should flow,<br>
Or how future floods could be softened below.</p>
<p>The budget looked tidy—at least for a year—<br>
But soon came the drought and the landslides and fear.<br>
For when you cut roots just to balance the sum,<br>
You find, all too late, that the green doesn’t come.</p>
<p>So next time you’re counting your dollars and cents,<br>
Remember: good planning is good common sense.<br>
A landscape’s not <em>pretty</em>, it’s how we all stay—<br>
It’s life in the soil, it’s work that won’t fade away.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="community-and-regional-planning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-and-regional-planning">Community and Regional Planning</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“When Planners Are Gone”</strong><br>
<em>A Villanelle</em></p>
<p>The maps grow blank where once the futures lay,<br>
Small towns fall silent, stripped of guiding hands;<br>
No one remains to chart a wiser way.</p>
<p>The roads still twist, the river bends its sway,<br>
But no one asks what promise each demands—<br>
The maps grow blank where once the futures lay.</p>
<p>The grain elevator rusts, the youth don’t stay,<br>
Old dreams collapse like barns in drifting sands;<br>
No one remains to chart a wiser way.</p>
<p>The county’s heart beats faint, its edges fray,<br>
Forgotten voices echo through their lands—<br>
The maps grow blank where once the futures lay.</p>
<p>The state grows proud of savings on display,<br>
Yet cannot count what loss the cut commands;<br>
No one remains to chart a wiser way.</p>
<p>So let the record show, in dust and clay:<br>
A vision died beneath their costed plans.<br>
The maps grow blank where once the futures lay—<br>
No one remains to chart a wiser way.</p>
</blockquote>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Already, ChatGPT is assuming an administration is more competent than ours is…↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Ok, so visual regression is an actual thing, thank you very much…↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>This is actually a better explanation than the one we got, which was “the metrics are the metrics, and we’re not changing them.”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Yep, we did actually offer this, but they did not take us up on that.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Again, this is a better explanation than what we got, which was… ignored.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>A random number generator might actually have better accuracy than the analysis method they used to eliminate our department, lol.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>post</category>
  <category>other</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/other/unl-program-cuts-shitposting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/cc/Facebook_AI_slop%2C_%22Shrimp_Jesus%22_1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Automated Residual Plot Assessment With the R Package autovi and the Shiny Application autovi.web</title>
  <dc:creator>Weihao Li, Dianne Cook, Emi Tanaka, Susan Vanderplas, Klaus Ackermann</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/liautomatedresidualplot.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/4oXZCAN.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Visual assessment of residual plots is a common approach for diagnosing linear models, but it relies on manual evaluation, which does not scale well and can lead to inconsistent decisions across analysts. The lineup protocol, which embeds the observed plot among null plots, can reduce subjectivity but requires even more human effort. In today’s data-driven world, such tasks are well suited for automation. We present a new R package that uses a computer vision model to automate the evaluation of residual plots. An accompanying Shiny application is provided for ease of use. Given a sample of residuals, the model predicts a visual signal strength ({VSS}) and offers supporting information to help analysts assess model fit.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-liAutomatedResidualPlot"></a>[1] W. Li, D. Cook, E. Tanaka, et al.&nbsp;“Automated Residual Plot Assessment With the R Package autovi and the Shiny Application autovi.web”. In: <em>Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Statistics</em> (Oct.&nbsp;09, 2025). ISSN: 1467-842X. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111%2Fanzs.70027">10.1111/anzs.70027</a>. URL: <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/anzs.70027">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/anzs.70027</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{liAutomatedResidualPlot,
  title = {Automated Residual Plot Assessment With the R Package autovi and the Shiny Application autovi.web},
  url = {https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/anzs.70027},
  doi = {10.1111/anzs.70027},
  author = {Weihao Li and Dianne Cook and Emi Tanaka and Susan Vanderplas and Klaus Ackermann},
  year = {2025},
  month = {10},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/liautomatedresidualplot.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/4oXZCAN.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Teaching Statistical Computing with R and Python</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/teaching-statistical-computing-with-r-and-python.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Computing courses can be daunting for students for a variety of reasons, including programming anxiety, difficulty learning a programming language in a second language, and unfamiliarity with assumed computer knowledge. In an ongoing attempt to teach statistical computing effectively, I developed a textbook intended for use in a flipped classroom setting where R and Python are taught concurrently. This approach allows students to learn programming concepts applicable to most languages, while developing skills in both R and Python that can be used in an increasingly multilingual field. In this talk, I discuss the book’s design and how it integrates into a sequence of undergraduate and graduate computing courses. Along the way, we will talk about opinionated coding decisions, use of memes, comics, and YouTube tutorials, and other features integrated into this open-source textbook built with quarto and hosted on GitHub.</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>, useR!
Event Type: Conference
Location: Durham, NC</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2025-Presentations/08-useR/#/title-slide" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/teaching-statistical-computing-with-r-and-python.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/teaching-statistical-computing-with-r-and-python.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="186" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hidden Multiple Comparisons Increase Forensic Error Rates</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/hidden-multiple-comparisons-increase-forensic-error-rates.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>When wires are cut, the tool produces striations on the cut surface; as in other forms of forensic analysis, these striation marks are used to connect the evidence to the source that created them. The practice of comparing two wire cut surfaces introduces complexities not present in better-investigated forensic examination of toolmarks such as those observed on bullets, as wire comparisons inherently require multiple distinct comparisons, increasing the error rate. We call attention to this multiple comparison problem in wire examination, and relate it to other situations in forensics that involve multiple comparisons, such as database searches.</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>Forensics Interest Group, Joint Statistical Meetings
Event Type: Conference
Location: Nashville, TN</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2025-Presentations/08-JSM/#/title-slide" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/hidden-multiple-comparisons-increase-forensic-error-rates.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/hidden-multiple-comparisons-increase-forensic-error-rates.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="62" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Guide to Designing Experiments to Test Statistical Graphics</title>
  <dc:creator>Emily Robinson, Heike Hofmann, Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/robinsonguidedesigningexperiments2025.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/qIoTTWh.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>In this paper, we discuss considerations and methods for experimentally testing visualizations. We discuss levels of user engagement with graphics, common issues when developing a sampling or data generation model, the importance of pilot testing, and data analysis methods. Along the way, we also provide recommendations of how to avoid some of the unique pitfalls of human testing in statistical and visualization research. This article is categorized under: Statistical and Graphical Methods of Data Analysis {<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%3E">} Statistical Graphics and Visualization Statistical and Graphical Methods of Data Analysis {<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%3E">} Modeling Methods and Algorithms</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-robinsonGuideDesigningExperiments2025"></a>[1] E. Robinson, H. Hofmann, and S. Vanderplas. “A Guide to Designing Experiments to Test Statistical Graphics”. In: <em>WIREs Computational Statistics</em> 17.2 (Jul.&nbsp;17, 2025), p.&nbsp;e70032. ISSN: 1939-0068. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002%2Fwics.70032">10.1002/wics.70032</a>. URL: <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/wics.70032">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/wics.70032</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{robinsonGuideDesigningExperiments2025,
  title = {A {{Guide}} to {{Designing Experiments}} to {{Test Statistical Graphics}}},
  author = {Emily Robinson and Heike Hofmann and Susan Vanderplas},
  year = {2025},
  month = {7},
  journal = {WIREs Computational Statistics},
  volume = {17},
  number = {2},
  pages = {e70032},
  doi = {10.1002/wics.70032},
  url = {https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/wics.70032},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/robinsonguidedesigningexperiments2025.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/qIoTTWh.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Can You See The Change? Visual Perception in Change Point Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Miguel Antonio Fudolig, Emily A. Robinson, Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/fudolig04042025.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/IC431w2.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Detecting change points is crucial in analyzing time series data and single-subject designs. This study investigates factors influencing change point detection through visual perception by employing a visual inference experiment. Participants were tasked with selecting the scatter plot that appeared most different from the surrounding plots. The” different” plot was generated to have a shift in the vertical direction compared to its counterparts with no vertical shift. We used a factorial experiment with a balanced incomplete block design to assign factor combinations for participants to evaluate. Furthermore, we compared the performance of visual accuracy to conventional change point detection methods. Participants were found to identify higher shift magnitudes more accurately than lower shift magnitudes, consistent with conventional methods. Change point data with higher variances had lower identification rates. Direction and change point location effects impacted identifying change point scenarios with lower signal-to-noise ratios. Participants indicated varying reasons for selection across correct and incorrect data plot identifications. Additionally, confidence in selection was positively associated with identification accuracy for change plots with higher signal-to-noise ratios. These insights highlight the complexities of change point detection through visual inference and emphasize the multifaceted nature of human perception in identifying subtle changes within data.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-Fudolig04042025"></a>[1] M. A. Fudolig, E. A. Robinson, and S. Vanderplas. “Can You See The Change? Visual Perception in Change Point Analysis”. In: <em>Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</em> (ja Apr.&nbsp;01, 2025), pp.&nbsp;1-15. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080%2F10618600.2025.2485278">10.1080/10618600.2025.2485278</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{Fudolig04042025,
  author = {Miguel Antonio Fudolig and Emily A. Robinson and Susan Vanderplas},
  title = {Can You See The Change? Visual Perception in Change Point Analysis},
  journal = {Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics},
  year = {2025},
  month = {4},
  pages = {1--15},
  doi = {10.1080/10618600.2025.2485278},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/fudolig04042025.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/IC431w2.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Perception and Cognitive Implications of Logarithmic Scales for Exponentially Increasing Data: Perceptual Sensitivity Tested with Statistical Lineups</title>
  <dc:creator>Emily A. Robinson, Reka Howard, Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/robinsonperceptioncognitiveimplications2025.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/JVvqE7P.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-robinsonPerceptionCognitiveImplications2025"></a>[1] E. A. Robinson, R. Howard, and S. Vanderplas. “Perception and Cognitive Implications of Logarithmic Scales for Exponentially Increasing Data: Perceptual Sensitivity Tested with Statistical Lineups”. In: <em>Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</em> (ja Mar.&nbsp;11, 2025), pp.&nbsp;1-14. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080%2F10618600.2025.2476097">10.1080/10618600.2025.2476097</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{robinsonPerceptionCognitiveImplications2025,
  author = {Emily A. Robinson and Reka Howard and Susan Vanderplas},
  title = {Perception and Cognitive Implications of Logarithmic Scales for Exponentially Increasing Data: Perceptual Sensitivity Tested with Statistical Lineups},
  pages = {1--14},
  year = {2025},
  month = {3},
  doi = {10.1080/10618600.2025.2476097},
  journal = {Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/robinsonperceptioncognitiveimplications2025.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/JVvqE7P.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Methodological problems in every black-box study of forensic firearm comparisons</title>
  <dc:creator>Maria Cuellar, Susan Vanderplas, Amanda Luby, Michael Rosenblum</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/cuellarmethodologicalproblemsevery2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/ec/NCI_swiss_cheese.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-cuellarMethodologicalProblemsEvery2024"></a>[1] M. Cuellar, S. Vanderplas, A. Luby, et al.&nbsp;“Methodological problems in every black-box study of forensic firearm comparisons”. In: <em>Law, Probability and Risk</em> 23.1 (Dec.&nbsp;05, 2024), p.&nbsp;mgae015. ISSN: 1470-8396. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.1093%2Flpr%2Fmgae015">https://doi.org/10.1093/lpr/mgae015</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{cuellarMethodologicalProblemsEvery2024,
  title = {Methodological problems in every black-box study of forensic firearm comparisons},
  volume = {23},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.1093/lpr/mgae015},
  number = {1},
  pages = {mgae015},
  journal = {Law, Probability and Risk},
  publisher = {Oxford University Press},
  author = {Maria Cuellar and Susan Vanderplas and Amanda Luby and Michael Rosenblum},
  year = {2024},
  month = {dec},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/cuellarmethodologicalproblemsevery2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/ec/NCI_swiss_cheese.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Creating Effective Graphics</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/creating-effective-graphics.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>How do we create effective charts and graphs for scientific presentations? What are the elements of effective charts and graphics? Which charts should be used for different types of data? How do we make charts that are “presentation ready”? In this workshop, we’ll do a quick run-through of guidelines for good charts and graphics, and then discuss how to use different scientific tools to create charts and graphics effectively.</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>, Undergraduate Creative Activities and Research Experience
Event Type: Department Seminar
Location: Lincoln, NE</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2024-Presentations/11-fyre-graphics/#/title-slide" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/creating-effective-graphics.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/creating-effective-graphics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incorrect statistical reasoning in Guyll et al. leads to biased claims about strength of forensic evidence</title>
  <dc:creator>Michael Rosenblum, Elizabeth T. Chin, Elizabeth L. Ogburn, Akihiko Nishimura, Daniel Westreich, Abhirup Datta, Susan Vanderplas, Maria Cuellar, William C. Thompson</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/rosenblumincorrectstatisticalreasoning2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://www.pnas.org/cms/10.1073/pnas.2315431121/asset/ed2391a4-340e-45d5-9699-fdd960bacd37/assets/images/large/pnas.2315431121fig01.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-rosenblumIncorrectStatisticalReasoning2024"></a>[1] M. Rosenblum, E. T. Chin, E. L. Ogburn, et al.&nbsp;“Incorrect statistical reasoning in Guyll et al.&nbsp;leads to biased claims about strength of forensic evidence”. In: <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em> 121.45 (Nov.&nbsp;05, 2024), p.&nbsp;e2315431121. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.1073%2Fpnas.2315431121">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2315431121</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{rosenblumIncorrectStatisticalReasoning2024,
  author = {Michael Rosenblum and Elizabeth T. Chin and Elizabeth L. Ogburn and Akihiko Nishimura and Daniel Westreich and Abhirup Datta and Susan Vanderplas and Maria Cuellar and William C. Thompson},
  title = {Incorrect statistical reasoning in {Guyll et al.} leads to biased claims about strength of forensic evidence},
  journal = {Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences},
  volume = {121},
  number = {45},
  pages = {e2315431121},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2315431121},
  publisher = {National Academy of Sciences},
  year = {2024},
  month = {nov},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/rosenblumincorrectstatisticalreasoning2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.pnas.org/cms/10.1073/pnas.2315431121/asset/ed2391a4-340e-45d5-9699-fdd960bacd37/assets/images/large/pnas.2315431121fig01.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Web Scraping Olympics: Python</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/web-scraping-olympics-python.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>A comparison of Python, Julia, and R for web-scraping Olympic athlete names, events, and birthdays. I represented python. See the full narrative here: https://srvanderplas.github.io/2024-data-jamboree-python/python-narrative.html</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>, Statistical Computing Section Mini-Symposium
Event Type: Webinar
Location: Online</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2024-Presentations/11-asa-computing/#/title-slide" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/web-scraping-olympics-python.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/web-scraping-olympics-python.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Plot is Worth a Thousand Tests: Assessing Residual Diagnostics with the Lineup Protocol</title>
  <dc:creator>Weihao (Patrick) Li, Di Cook, Emi Tanaka, Klaus Ackermann, Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/a-plot-is-worth-a-thousand-tests-assessing-residual-diagnostics-with-the-lineup-protocol.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Regression experts consistently recommend plotting residuals for model diagnosis, despite the availability of many numerical hypothesis test procedures designed to use residuals to assess problems with a model fit. Here we provide evidence for why this is good advice using data from a visual inference experiment. We show how conventional tests are too sensitive, which means that too often the conclusion would be that the model fit is inadequate. The experiment uses the lineup protocol which puts a residual plot in the context of null plots. This helps generate reliable and consistent reading of residual plots for better model diagnosis. It can also help in an obverse situation where a conventional test would fail to detect a problem with a model due to contaminated data. The lineup protocol also detects a range of departures from good residuals simultaneously.</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>Section on Statistical Graphics, JSM
Event Type: Conference
Location: Portland, Or</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2024-Presentations/08-JSM/" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/a-plot-is-worth-a-thousand-tests-assessing-residual-diagnostics-with-the-lineup-protocol.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/a-plot-is-worth-a-thousand-tests-assessing-residual-diagnostics-with-the-lineup-protocol.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="58" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Escaping Flatland: Graphics, Dimensionality, andHuman Perception</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas, Erin Blankenship, Tyler Wiederich</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/vanderplasescapingflatlandgraphics2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://github.com/srvanderplas/2024-hcii-escaping-flatland/blob/main/image/Kit_of_charts.png?raw=true" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Almost 40~years ago, Cleveland and McGill published the first of 3 papers detailing experiments assessing the accuracy of numerical perception using different types of charts. This study is often cited as a reason to avoid the use of extraneous dimensions in data visualization: 2D bar charts produced more accurate estimates than 3D bar charts; in addition, lines (length) produced more accurate estimates than circles (area). Graphics have changed fairly significantly in the last 40~years: where we once had fixed 3D perspective charts, we now can rotate 3D renderings in digital space and even 3D print our charts to examine physically. Many optical illusions result from perceptual mismatches of 3D visual heuristics and 2D, planar, data representations; more realistic renderings available with modern tools might change the outcome of Cleveland and McGill’s experimental comparison of 2D vs.~3D accuracy. In this paper, we present several experiments which replicate the bar chart portion of Cleveland and McGill’s original study, comparing 2D, 3D fixed perspective, 3D rendered, and 3D printed charts. We discuss the findings and the importance of replicating classic experiments using modern technology, as well as the benefits of incorporating hands-on research in introductory classes as experiential learning activities.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-vanderplasEscapingFlatlandGraphics2024"></a>[1] S. Vanderplas, E. Blankenship, and T. Wiederich. “Escaping Flatland: Graphics, Dimensionality, and~Human Perception”. In: <em>Human Interface and the Management of Information</em>. Ed. by H. Mori and Y. Asahi. Springer Nature Switzerland, Jul.&nbsp;01, 2024, pp.&nbsp;140-156. ISBN: 978-3-031-60114-9. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.1007%2F978-3-031-60114-9_11">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-60114-9_11</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@inproceedings{vanderplasEscapingFlatlandGraphics2024,
  title = {Escaping {Flatland}: {Graphics}, {Dimensionality}, and~{Human Perception}},
  booktitle = {Human {Interface} and the {Management} of {Information}},
  author = {Susan Vanderplas and Erin Blankenship and Tyler Wiederich},
  editor = {Hirohiko Mori and Yumi Asahi},
  year = {2024},
  pages = {140--156},
  publisher = {Springer Nature Switzerland},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-60114-9_11},
  month = {jul},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://github.com/srvanderplas/2024-hcii-escaping-flatland" class="btn btn-tip"><i class="fa-brands fa-github fa-2x" aria-label="github"></i> Repository for Paper and Additional Resources</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/vanderplasescapingflatlandgraphics2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://github.com/srvanderplas/2024-hcii-escaping-flatland/blob/main/image/Kit_of_charts.png?raw=true" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Escaping Flatland: Graphics, Dimensionality, and Human Perception</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/escaping-flatland-graphics-dimensionality-and-human-perception.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Almost 40 years ago, Cleveland &amp; McGill published the first of 3 papers detailing experiments assessing the accuracy of numerical perception using different types of charts. This study is often cited as a reason to avoid the use of extraneous dimensions in data visualization: 2D bar charts produced more accurate estimates than 3D bar charts; in addition, lines (length) produced more accurate estimates than circles (area). Graphics have changed fairly significantly in the last 40 years: where we once had fixed 3D perspective charts, we now can rotate 3D renderings in digital space and even 3D print our charts to examine physically. Many optical illusions result from perceptual mismatches of 3D visual heuristics and 2D, planar, data representations; more realistic renderings available with modern tools might change the outcome of the Cleveland &amp; McGill comparison of 2D vs.&nbsp;3D accuracy. In this paper, we present several experiments which replicate the bar chart portion of Cleveland &amp; McGill’s original study, comparing 2D, 3D fixed perspective, 3D rendered, and 3D printed charts. We discuss the findings and the importance of replicating classic experiments using modern technology, as well as the benefits of incorporating hands-on research in introductory classes as experiential learning activities.</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>, Human Computer Interaction International
Event Type: Conference
Location: Washington DC</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2024-Presentations/07-HCII/#/title-slide" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/escaping-flatland-graphics-dimensionality-and-human-perception.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/escaping-flatland-graphics-dimensionality-and-human-perception.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="99" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Creating Good Graphics</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/creating-good-graphics.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Let’s talk about how to create good charts and graphics!</p>
</section>
<section id="location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="location">Location</h2>
<pre><code>University of Nebraska - Lincoln, UNL REU seminar
Event Type: Department Seminar
Location: Lincoln, NE</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides">Slides</h2>
<iframe src="https://srvanderplas.github.io/2024-Presentations/06-REU-graphics/#/title-slide" height="800px" width="500px">
</iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>talks</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/creating-good-graphics.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="srvanderplas.github.io/posts/talks/creating-good-graphics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="106" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hidden Multiple Comparisons Increase Forensic Error Rates</title>
  <dc:creator>Susan Vanderplas, Alicia Carriquiry, Heike Hofmann</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/vanderplashiddenmultiplecomparisons2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/JXILntV.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>When wires are cut, the tool produces striations on the cut surface; as in other forms of forensic analysis, these striation marks are used to connect the evidence to the source that created them. Here, we argue that the practice of comparing two wire cut surfaces introduces complexities not present in better-investigated forensic examination of toolmarks such as those observed on bullets, as wire comparisons inherently require multiple distinct comparisons, increasing the expected false discovery rate. We call attention to the multiple comparison problem in wire examination and relate it to other situations in forensics that involve multiple comparisons, such as database searches.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-vanderplasHiddenMultipleComparisons2024"></a>[1] S. Vanderplas, A. Carriquiry, and H. Hofmann. “Hidden Multiple Comparisons Increase Forensic Error Rates”. In: <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em> 121.25 (Jun.&nbsp;10, 2024), p.&nbsp;e2401326121. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.1073%2Fpnas.2401326121">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2401326121</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{vanderplasHiddenMultipleComparisons2024,
  title = {Hidden Multiple Comparisons Increase Forensic Error Rates},
  author = {Susan Vanderplas and Alicia Carriquiry and Heike Hofmann},
  year = {2024},
  month = {6},
  journal = {Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences},
  volume = {121},
  number = {25},
  pages = {e2401326121},
  publisher = {National Academy of Sciences},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2401326121},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://github.com/srvanderplas/Wire-Cut-Errors" class="btn btn-tip"><i class="fa-brands fa-github fa-2x" aria-label="github"></i> Repository for Paper and Additional Resources</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/vanderplashiddenmultiplecomparisons2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/JXILntV.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Plot Is Worth a Thousand Tests: Assessing Residual Diagnostics with the Lineup Protocol</title>
  <dc:creator>Weihao Li, Dianne Cook, Emi Tanaka, Susan VanderPlas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/liplotworththousand2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/4ofhYGn.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Regression experts consistently recommend plotting residuals for model diagnosis, despite the availability of many numerical hypothesis test procedures designed to use residuals to assess problems with a model fit. Here we provide evidence for why this is good advice using data from a visual inference experiment. We show how conventional tests are too sensitive, which means that too often the conclusion would be that the model fit is inadequate. The experiment uses the lineup protocol which puts a residual plot in the context of null plots. This helps generate reliable and consistent reading of residual plots for better model diagnosis. It can also help in an obverse situation where a conventional test would fail to detect a problem with a model due to contaminated data. The lineup protocol also detects a range of departures from good residuals simultaneously.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-liPlotWorthThousand2024"></a>[1] W. Li, D. Cook, E. Tanaka, et al.&nbsp;“A Plot Is Worth a Thousand Tests: Assessing Residual Diagnostics with the Lineup Protocol”. In: <em>Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</em> (May. 22, 2024), pp.&nbsp;1497-1511. ISSN: 1061-8600. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.1080%2F10618600.2024.2344612">https://doi.org/10.1080/10618600.2024.2344612</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{liPlotWorthThousand2024,
  title = {A {{Plot}} Is {{Worth}} a {{Thousand Tests}}: {{Assessing Residual Diagnostics}} with the {{Lineup Protocol}}},
  author = {Weihao Li and Dianne Cook and Emi Tanaka and Susan VanderPlas},
  year = {2024},
  month = {5},
  pages = {1497--1511},
  journal = {Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics},
  publisher = {Taylor &amp; Francis},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.1080/10618600.2024.2344612},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://github.com/TengMCing/lineup_residual_diagnostics" class="btn btn-tip"><i class="fa-brands fa-github fa-2x" aria-label="github"></i> Repository for Paper and Additional Resources</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/liplotworththousand2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/4ofhYGn.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Demonstrative Evidence and the Use of Algorithms in Jury Trials</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Rogers, Susan VanderPlas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/rogersdemonstrativeevidenceuse2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/ae6Sa8U.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>We investigate how the use of bullet comparison algorithms and demonstrative evidence may affect juror perceptions of reliability, credibility, and understanding of expert witnesses and presented evidence. The use of statistical methods in forensic science is motivated by a lack of scientific validity and error rate issues present in many forensic analysis methods. We explore what our study says about how this type of forensic evidence is perceived in the courtroom – where individuals unfamiliar with advanced statistical methods are asked to evaluate results in order to assess guilt. In the course of our initial study, we found that individuals overwhelmingly provided high Likert scale ratings in reliability, credibility, and scientificity regardless of experimental condition. This discovery of scale compression - where responses are limited to a few values on a larger scale, despite experimental manipulations - limits statistical modeling but provides opportunities for new experimental manipulations which may improve future studies in this area.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-rogersDemonstrativeEvidenceUse2024"></a>[1] R. Rogers and S. VanderPlas. “Demonstrative Evidence and the Use of Algorithms in Jury Trials”. In: <em>Journal of Data Science</em> 22.2 (May. 02, 2024), pp.&nbsp;314-332. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.6339%2F24-JDS1130">https://doi.org/10.6339/24-JDS1130</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{rogersDemonstrativeEvidenceUse2024,
  author = {Rachel Rogers and Susan VanderPlas},
  title = {Demonstrative {{Evidence}} and the {{Use}} of {{Algorithms}} in {{Jury Trials}}},
  journal = {Journal of Data Science},
  year = {2024},
  month = {5},
  volume = {22},
  number = {2},
  pages = {314--332},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.6339/24-JDS1130},
  publisher = {School of Statistics, Renmin University of China},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://github.com/rachelesrogers/Algorithms_in_Jury_Trials" class="btn btn-tip"><i class="fa-brands fa-github fa-2x" aria-label="github"></i> Repository for Paper and Additional Resources</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/rogersdemonstrativeevidenceuse2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/ae6Sa8U.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Evaluating Perceptual Judgements on 3D Printed Bar Charts</title>
  <dc:creator>Tyler Wiederich, Susan Vanderplas</dc:creator>
  <link>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/wiederichevaluatingperceptualjudgements2024.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/QCPSE4V.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<p>Graphical design principles typically recommend minimizing the dimensionality of a visualization - for instance, using only 2 dimensions for bar charts rather than providing a 3D rendering, because this extra complexity may result in a decrease in accuracy. This advice has been oft repeated, but the underlying experimental evidence is focused on fixed 2D projections of 3D charts. In this paper, we describe an experiment which attempts to establish whether the decrease in accuracy extends to 3D virtual renderings and 3D printed charts. We replicate the grouped bar chart comparisons in the 1984 Cleveland &amp; {McGill} study, assessing the accuracy of numerical estimates using different types of 3D and 2D renderings.</p>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a name="bib-wiederichEvaluatingPerceptualJudgements2024"></a>[1] T. Wiederich and S. Vanderplas. “Evaluating Perceptual Judgements on 3D Printed Bar Charts”. In: <em>Journal of Data Science</em> 22.2 (Apr.&nbsp;24, 2024), pp.&nbsp;176-190. ISSN: 1680743X. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/https%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.6339%2F24-JDS1131">https://doi.org/10.6339/24-JDS1131</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center collapsed" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Bibtex
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<pre><code>@article{wiederichEvaluatingPerceptualJudgements2024,
  title = {Evaluating Perceptual Judgements on 3D Printed Bar Charts},
  volume = {22},
  doi = {https://doi.org/10.6339/24-JDS1131},
  pages = {176--190},
  number = {2},
  journal = {Journal of Data Science},
  author = {Tyler Wiederich and Susan Vanderplas},
  publisher = {School of Statistics, Renmin University of China},
  year = {2024},
  month = {4},
  author+AN = {1=student;2=highlight},
}</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://github.com/TWiedRW/2023-JDS-3dcharts" class="btn btn-tip"><i class="fa-brands fa-github fa-2x" aria-label="github"></i> Repository for Paper and Additional Resources</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>papers</category>
  <guid>srvanderplas.github.io/posts/papers/wiederichevaluatingperceptualjudgements2024.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/QCPSE4V.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
